garcy now democracynow.org the war and
peace report I'm Amy Goodman with
nermeen Shaikh a retired CIA agent who
blew the whistle on the agency's
bush-era torture program has been
sentenced to two and a half years in
prison John Kiriakou becomes the first
CIA official to be jailed for any reason
relating to the torture program under a
plea deal Kiriakou admitted to a single
count of violating the intelligence
identities Protection Act by revealing
the identity of a covert officer to a
freelance reporter who did not publish
it under the plea deal prosecutors
dropped charges brought under the
Espionage Act in 2007 Kiriakou became
the first CIA official to publicly
confirm and detail the Bush
administration's use of waterboarding
when he spoke to ABC's Brian Ross at the
time I felt that waterboarding was
something that we needed to do and as
time has passed and has September 11th
has has you know has moved farther and
farther back into history I think I've
changed my mind and I think that
waterboarding is probably something that
we shouldn't be in the business of doing
why do you say that no because we're
Americans and we're better than that
John Kiriakou supporters say he has been
unfairly targeted in the Obama
administration's crackdown on government
whistleblowers in a statement urging
President Obama to commute kiriakos
sentence a group of signatories
including attorneys and former CIA
officers said quote Kiriakou is an anti
torture whistleblower who spoke out
against torture because he believed it
violated his oath to the Constitution
please mr. president
do not allow your legacy to be one where
only the whistleblower goes to jail
prosecutor Neal McBride the US attorney
for the Eastern District of Virginia
defended the government's handling of
the case as the judge just said in court
today's sentence should be a reminder to
every individual who works for the
government who comes into the possession
of closely-held sensitive information
regarding the national defense or the
identity of a covert agent that it is
critical to that information remain
secure and not spill out into the public
domain or be shared with others who
don't have authorized access to it
John Kiriakou joins us now from
Washington DC spent 14 years at the CIA
as an analyst and a case officer in 2002
we led the team that found Abu Zubaydah
a high-ranking member of al-qaeda he's
father of five
in 2010 he published a memoir entitled
the reluctant spy my secret life in the
CIA's war on terror and we're joined by
one of John kiriakos attorneys jesselyn
Radack she's the director of national
security and human rights at the
Government Accountability Project a
former ethics adviser to the United
States Department of Justice we reached
out to the US Attorney's Office for the
Eastern District of Virginia but they
declined our request for an interview
John Kerry aku why are you going to jail
explain the plea deal you made with the
government well thanks first of all for
having me and giving me the opportunity
to to explain I'm going to prison
ostensibly for violating the
intelligence identities Protection Act
of 1982 I believe and my supporters
believe that this however was not a case
about leaking this was a case about
torture and I believe I'm going to
prison because I blew the whistle on
torture I've been a thorn in the CIA
side since that interview in 2007 in
which I said that waterboarding was
torture and that it was official US
government policy and I think finally
the Justice Department caught up with me
jesselyn Radack let me just bring you
into the conversation to explain what
the intelligence identities Protection
Act is
your client John Kiriakou it's been
invoked in his case for the first time
in 27 years that's correct in fact there
have only been two convictions under the
intelligence identities Protection Act
which was enacted to prevent cases like
Philip Agee not things like John
Kiriakou it was to prevent the revealing
of covert identities for profit or to
aid the enemy in this case john
confirmed the name of a torturer to a
journalist which makes neil mcbride
statement all the more hypocritical
because the biggest leaker of classified
information including sources and
methods and undercover identities has
been the US government john kerry aku
explain what it is that you were trying
to expose explain what you were involved
with talk about Abu Zubaydah your
involvement in the finding of him and
then the course you took where your
conscience took you sure in in 2002 I
was the chief of counterterrorism
operations for the CIA in Pakistan and
my job was to try to locate al-qaeda
fighters or al Qaeda leaders and capture
them to turn them over to to the Justice
Department and and have them face trial
that was the original the original idea
not to have them sit in Cuba for the
next decade but we caught up with
Zubaydah he was shot three times by
Pakistani police as he was trying to
escape from his safe house and and I was
the first person to to have custody of
him to sit with him we spoke to each
other extensively
I mean talked about everything from
September 11th to poetry that he had
been writing to his family and and then
he was moved on to a secret prison after
that once I got back to headquarters I
heard that he had been subject to two
harsh techniques then you've amidst
eclis called enhanced interrogation
techniques and I was asked
one of the leaders in the CIA's
counter-terrorist Center if I wanted to
be trained in the use of these
techniques I told him that I had a moral
problem with them and I did not want to
be involved so fast-forward to 2007 by
then Human Rights Watch and Amnesty
International had reported that al-qaeda
prisoners had been tortured and ABC News
called and said that they had
information that I had tortured Abu
Zubaydah I said that was absolutely
untrue
I was the only person who was kind to
Abu Zubaydah and I had never tortured
anybody so they asked me to go on their
show and defend myself I did that and in
the course of the interview I said that
not only was the CIA torturing prisoners
but that it was official US government
policy this was not the result of some
rogue CIA officer just beating up a
prisoner every once in a while this was
official policy that went all the way up
to the President of the United States
and so what happened after that
in 2007 once you gave this interview can
you explain what happened to you and and
to your family sure within 24 hours the
CIA filed what's called a crimes report
against me with the Justice Department
saying that I had revealed classified
information which was the torture
program and asking for an investigation
with an eye toward prosecuting me the
Justice Department decided at the time
that I had not revealed classified
information that the information was
already in the public domain but
immediately within weeks I was audited
by the IRS
I've been audited by the IRS every
single year since giving that interview
in 2007 but a more important bit of
fallout from that interview was that
every time I would write an op-ed every
time I would give a television interview
or give a speech at a university the CIA
would file a crimes report against me
accusing me of leaking additional
classified information each time the
Justice Department determined that I did
not leak any classified information in
fact I would get those op-eds and those
speeches cleared by the CIA's
publication's Review Board in a
then the CIA started harassing my wife
who at the time was a senior CIA officer
particularly over an op-ed I had written
they accused her of leaking classified
information to me for the purpose of
writing the op-ed well I said I had
gotten the information in in the op-ed
from two UPI reports and from a South
American Ministry of Foreign Affairs
website and they would back off but this
this sort of became our life we would be
under FBI surveillance she would be
called into the CIA's office of security
I would have trouble getting a security
clearance when I went to Capitol Hill it
just became this pattern of harassment
so John why didn't you stop because I
think that that torture is something
that needs to be discussed I said this
in 2007 this is something that we should
about which we should it be having a
national debate and frankly I have a
First Amendment right to free speech and
you know writing an op-ed is not against
the law giving a speech about the Arab
Spring or about torture is not against
the law and I felt that that I didn't
want to be cowed I didn't want to be
frightened into silence by the CIA and
John Kiriakou you said that in these
instances that you've named you were
actually charged with espionage is that
right can you talk about the
significance of the Espionage Act yes
the government initially charged me with
three counts of espionage I'm it sounds
silly maybe but I'm still personally
offended by these espionage charges
which which were dropped of course the
the espionage charge is is used as a
hammer by the administration to force
people into silence my espionage charge
is related to a conversation that I had
with a New York Times reporter a New
York Times reporter approached me and
said that he was writing a story about a
colleague of mine and what I grant him
an interview I gave him the interview I
said this colleague was a great guy the
unsung hero of the Abu Zubaydah
operation terrific officer
the reporter said do you know how I can
get in touch with him and I said no I've
been out of touch with him for a while
but I think I might have his business
card so I gave the reporter of the
business card now mind you this is a CIA
officer who had never ever been
undercover his business card showed that
he was involved as a CIA contractor and
it had his personal email on it and his
cell phone number I gave the reporter
the business card and was charged with
two counts of espionage I later gave the
same business card to another journalist
who was doing an article and was charged
with a third count of espionage what is
it that you allege the CIA was doing for
all of these years explained the torture
program that you were trying to expose
sure there were there were something
like ten different techniques that were
used in the CIA's torture program they
went from the benign you know where
where an officer would grab a prisoner
by the lapels and give him a shake all
the way up to the really rough things
that we've heard about like
waterboarding or what I think is worse
sleep deprivation or the cold cell where
they'll put a prisoner naked in a Cell
chilled to fifty or fifty-five degrees
and then every hour to throw ice water
on him
I actually think those last two are
worse than waterboarding but again these
are techniques that we have condemned
other countries for throughout history
the Japanese did this during the Second
World War
the Belgians did it in in Africa earlier
in the century the Chinese and the
Vietnamese did it this is these are
techniques that we have always said were
crimes against humanity and then it was
though it was though after September
11th everything changed and we somehow
had license to do the same things we had
been condemning I thought that was wrong
you know director Petraeus former
director Petraeus made a statement in
October when I agreed to take a plea to
make these other charges go away and he
said that my conviction shows that we
have to take our oaths seriously why
took my oath seriously my oath was to
the Constitution on my first day in the
CIA I put my right hand up and I swore
to uphold the Constitution and to me
torture is unconstitutional and it's
something that we should not be in the
business of doing John Kiriakou I want
to play for you comments President Obama
made four years ago shortly before he
took office about whether CIA officials
involved in torture should be prosecuted
he appeared on the ABC News this week I
don't believe that anybody is above the
law on the other hand I also have a
belief that we need to look forward as
lows as opposed to look looking
backwards and part of my job is to make
sure that for example at the CIA
you've got extraordinarily talented
people who are working very hard to keep
Americans safe I don't want them to
suddenly feel like they've got to spend
all their time we're looking over their
shoulders and laws no 911 Commission
with independency in a pound oh well we
have not made final decisions but my
instinct is for us to focus on how do we
make sure that moving forward we are
doing the right thing that was President
Obama speaking four years ago to ABC
John Kiriakou your response to what the
president said I supported the
president's response I remember that
interview and I thought okay he's right
there are wonderful talented
hard-working men and women at the CIA
who need to be protected but at the same
time it's one thing to look forward it's
another thing to look forward just for
the torturers it's just not fair it's
not fair to the American people if we're
going to if we're going to make
prosecutions or initiate prosecutions
those prosecutions can't just be against
the people who who blew the whistle on
the torturer who opposed to who opposed
the torture you know we haven't we
haven't even investigated the torturers
as jessalyn said we haven't initiated
any actions against the people who
conceived of the torture implemented the
policy or against the man who destroyed
evidence of the torture were against the
attorneys who used specious legal
arguments to justify the torture if
we're gonna move forward let's move
forward but you can't target one person
or two people who blew the whistle
junkier you've also spoken about
witnessing new foreign service officers
being confirmed foreign services
officers who were previously with the
CIA and participated in acts of torture
could you explain what happened and
explain its significance yes when I was
a senior investigator on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee I was
approached by a journalist who said that
he had evidence that the CIA was
misusing its cover agreement with the
State Department to place people
involved in the torture program under
State Department covers so that their
names could not be exposed in the press
and if those names were exposed in the
press the the people giving the names
would be subject to the intelligence
identities Protection Act so again this
was a violation of the of the CIA State
Department cover agreement I sent a
letter under Senator John Kerry then
Senator John Kerry's signature asking
the CIA for clarification I got a
response about six weeks later that was
classified top secret so I was not
permitted to see the response I did not
have a top secret clearance at the time
and a colleague of mine told me that the
letter essentially said in very strongly
worded language to mind my own business
we're gonna go to break and we come back
we want to ask you about President
Obama's nominee to become the next set
of the CIA John Brennan because as you
talked about the administration we're
talking actually about administration's
from the Bush administration to the
Obama administration our guest is about
to go to jail his name is John Kiriakou
he's about to serve two and a half years
in jail these this will be one of his
last interviews wherefore he goes to
prison will joined also by jesselyn
Radack who is one of his attorneys stay
with us thanks so much for watching this
report from Democracy Now your daily
independent global news hour we don't
accept advertising or corporate funding
but rather rely on donations from
viewers like you please make your
contribution by visiting
democracynow.org we need your support
today to keep
bring you this hard-hitting in-depth
reporting
you